Latin American mss. --Paraguay, 1640/1862 LMC 1626
Lilly Library
Latin American mss. --Paraguay
1640-1862
Lilly Library
LMC 1626
1 folio
5 bound
The Latin American mss. --Paraguay, 1640-1862, consists of individual items acquired separately either as a gift, purchase, transfer, or removal from a variety of sources, relating to Paraguay. Additions continue to be made.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Scope and Content Note
The Latin American mss. Paraguay, 1640-1862, consist principally of materials related to the indigenous peoples and the Catholic missions of Paraguay. Other manuscripts deal with military privileges, ecclesiastical patronage and finances, and the proposal for founding a university in Asuncion.
Bound volumes in the collection include Jose Sanchez Labrador's Paraguay Catholico en sus Principales Provincias reducidas a la Santa Fe and Paraguay Catholico: Harmonioso Entable de las missiones de los Indios Guaranis, written in 1772, which contain maps and vary from his printed work El Paraguay catolico, Buenos Aires, Imprenta de Coni Hermanos, 1910 (BV2853 .P2S211); Missiones vivas de la Compana de Jesus del Paraguay written by Ignacio Joseph Gonzalez in the eighteenth century; Silex de el el Divino amor y Rapto activo de el animo, en la Memoria, Ententimiento y voluntad, a theological work written in 1640 by the Jesuit missionary Antonio Ruiz de Montoya; and a book of devotions, Specvlvm Sine Macvla dated about 1750.
The Specvlvm Sine Macvla was possibly hand copied by a Guarani Indian for a Jesuit missionary. This manuscript was given by Saturnino Segurola y Lezica to Sir Woodbine Parish in 1824. In 1862 Parish sent it to Henry Hucks Gibbs, baron Aldenham. The manuscript also has the bookplate of Oscar E. Carbone of Buenos Aires, Argentina.
The correspondents are Carlos III, king of Spain; Jose de Armendariz, marques de Castelfuerte; Tomas Donvidas; Francisco Antonio Escudero de Rozas; Fernando VI, king of Spain; Jose Gaspar Rodriguez Francia; Antonio Olaguer y Feliu Heredia Lopez y Donec; Sir Woodbine Parish; Alonso Portillo; Juan Jose Priego; and Jaime Sanjust.
Note on Indexing Term - "Law": There is a large quantity of legal material pertaining to Latin America in these collections. Royal and viceregal decrees, both de oficio and de parte, are especially numerous.
Note on Indexing Term - "Religion": A large quantity of this material relates to religious matters.
Note on Indexing Term - "West (U.S.)" and "Americana": There are items pertaining to early settlements and colonial government in Texas, California and New Mexico, and information on Texas independence.
For digitized content, see Digital Collections.
Acquisition Information
Acquired
Missions--Early works to 1800.; International relations; Law; Religion; Americana; West (U.S.); Paraguay--History.; Catholic Church--Missions.; Jesuits--Missions--Paraguay.
- I. 1685-1862
  - 1685-1750 (Foliobox 10)
  - 1750-1800 (Foliobox 10)
  - 1800-1862 (Foliobox 10)
- II. Individually Boxed Items
  - Ruiz de Montoya. Silex..., 1640 (Bound 1)
  - Specvlvm Sine Macvla..., [1750?] (Bound 2)
  - Sanchez Labrador. Paraguay Catholico..., 1772 (Bound 3)
  - Sanchez Labrador. Paraguay Catholico..., 1772 (Bound 4)
  - Ignacio Joseph Gonzalez. Misiones Vivas., n.d. (Bound 5)
- III. Oversize
  - In nome S.M. Vittorio Emanuele II Re D'Italia..., 1874, July 12 (Folder 1)
  - Exercito de [?]tramar..., 1817, Sept. 10 (Folder 1)
  - Exercito de [?]tramar..., 1817, Mar. 10 (Folder 1)